and a big fire there as they exited out
of turn three and that looks very nasty
indeed
this this was a big one is he okay i've
seen it to the mirrors no
please
is everyone okay is he out
how's he gonna help oh tell him he's
okay please tell me he's okay are they
okay i see you're fired is everyone
alright this car is on the player
he's out
is he is he okay
i could feel my hands with burning you
know where normally when you that you
touch something hot you would you touch
it and remove it but i would i would
keep my hands straight into the fire
because that's the only
grip i had to jump out of the car
my foot was stuck and i was pulling so
hard on my leg that even my ankle could
have stayed there i wouldn't care you
know i just wanted to be out of the car
at one point i thought that was it that
was my day you know
that was game over
hi roman thank you so much for taking
the time for a chat where are we finding
you
hey hey hi i'm you know i'm i'm good i'm
i'm back in switzerland where i uh i
live with the family for some time and
between all the travel in the us i like
to be home and and quiet so there's
going to be quite a few back and forth
this year how many flights how many
flights have you scheduled so far
uh i mean they changed every day we
covered you know you book one in the
next hour it's cancelled so you need to
go to the next one
and uh it's a bit of a challenge but uh
i mean you know it's good fun and uh i
guess i'll be quite used to jet lag at
the end of the year
so you know that you know that i worked
with a harvard um uh harvard sleep
trainer on jet lag during my
championship year and i don't know if
you've looked into something like that
but the secret was
to do small steps especially if you're
going like for a longer period so you
start at home one and a half hours per
day and then when you get there you
continue doing one and a half hours per
day this way you don't have any jet lag
at all i don't know maybe you can uh try
something like that as well yeah i did
try when when i was in formula one and
it actually works quite well when you go
to asia with the kids because you go to
bed early and earlier you know you end
up going to bed at seven and waking
about like five or four
but going to the us with their kids is
impossible because then i end up going
to bed at 1 am and the kids at 6 30 they
wake me up and i said daddy let's go
play so
i've given up
so most of the time you're taking the
family over there as well or something
no they stay here and uh this this
summer we will go there i think we will
have a big rv and we're gonna go on and
drive around the country and discover
something new that sounds awesome that's
a nice new step of life no
yeah exactly it's very different i found
the atmosphere there absolutely amazing
such a warm welcome and back to basics
and racing and that feels good that's
cool that's nice nice to hear i want to
jump to the beginning of your career
like where was the where did the dream
start for you to like be f1 driver
fighting for for big things where was
the beginning of the dream
it was all it was always my dad uh you
know he was he was always passionate
about racing cars and uh he started
competing himself when he was about 40
so i was what eight years old and uh
coming with him on the races and seeing
the cars and
then he bought himself a go-kart to
practice to to do some formula three in
the swiss championship
and uh he bought
he bought me one and i jumped in the
go-kart and then every wednesday
afternoon every saturday morning i was
at the track
and eventually asked to go racing and
that's how it all went and did you like
did you ever believe like yes i can do
this i could be a formula one driver or
did it like evolve like
what was your thinking
i know in old fairness i had no idea i
could make it until i was in formula two
uh just because you know you go card
with so many other races you know and
then you go
through the categories and then there's
only 20 seats at the top of the of the
ladder in formula one so you know it's
it's a very steep pyramid
and um
[Music]
what eventually when i when i made it to
do gp2 at the time uh and i started
winning races i thought oh you know what
maybe i can maybe i can make it but
beforehand it was just uh going racing
and having fun and so in gp2 you
actually thought yes i can do this i can
i can become a former one driver yeah in
gp2 i thought you know if i can win the
category just under formula one and and
compete with the the top guys here then
i think i have a chance so that's
already more than more the more
confidence that i ever had i was never
even in the last step i was i was not
convinced that i could race the likes of
shoemakers montoya's you know who were
racing in my time uh
i don't know i never had that big um big
self-confidence anyway so then you won
formula three gp2 but before before
winning gp2 of course you were renault
test driver 2009
and suddenly out of the blue
you get called up to get to jump into
the race seat
like with not so much practice and right
in against the toughest opponent in the
world at the time which was fernando
alonso in his absolute prime
can you take us through a little bit how
that like that moment was of finding out
okay i'm actually gonna get the race
seat next to alonso now and i'm not
really prepared and like was it just
exciting or was it like oh i don't
know if i'm gonna manage to do this so
well or what was the feelings i think i
think it was just excitement because if
i give you the background so yes i was i
was a honor test driver for a long time
even though the r29 i think was named in
2009 i never drove it until i got to
valencia free practice one never even
you know i made my seat and that was it
there were no simulator at the time so i
didn't practice anything um
and i was i was leading the gp2
and then i got the phone call after
germany you are in the car in hungary
next week so i'm all excited ready for
it you know it was it was pat simons
call me calling me
and then uh the next day i got a phone
call nothing got no actually nelson has
got the last chance he will do hungary
so i'm like oh okay i'm back to gp2 so
you know i mean it was great to be gp2
is amazing but when you have the call
that you're gonna be in the car
in the formula one and then they call
you back and say no you're not it was a
bit of a disappointment
and then eventually i get the cold again
uh before the summer break or during the
summer break okay in valencia are you in
the car
it is seven grand please to practice to
warm up no pressure no need of results
the car is anywhere not good uh just
take it as a as a learning curve and
2010 you're in the car uh with a you
know much better situation so for me
there was no real impression that where
that
it was seven grand priests to learn what
formula one is and
well didn't turn up to me that way
i'm surprised that you say there's no
pressure because for a young driver
you only have a handful of moments to
impress
and and to tell everybody okay you
deserve to be there so i'm surprised
that you were able to still keep it so
so light-hearted in a way so that's
that's a good mindset i think yeah i
think and you know obviously because
you're told it's it's like practice
because you never race the car obviously
going to the grid there were pressure on
you know when it's your first grandpa
you want to do well and so on but
if you if you take the old picture it
was like yeah you know it's it's a
practice for you we don't expect
anything from you uh we don't you know
no no pressure was the word
and uh and then the crash gate story
appeared i was i was managed by flavio
at the time
and uh you know when when everything was
was was happening they cleared the whole
house and i was clear with the furniture
yeah
you that crash gate cost me the win by
the way in singapore at the time
so
that was uh i also have a connection to
that um you're racing you're racing
alonzo then in those seven races
he was in his super prime he's one of
the best of all time do you remember any
like moments where like oh my god what
what is this guy doing like do you
remember some some crazy insane moments
one one in in suzuka and qualifying i
was they were weak and i was i was
faster than him in three practice and
comes qualifying the first set of tires
i'm faster than him
and then the second set of tar he kills
me and i'm like
damn you know what happened here and i
go and open the data and i remember
spoon corner you know we used to i don't
know we used to break a little bit for
the first part then lift off the break
and then breaking
i mean the first part he went in so fast
like instantly fast it wasn't the same
corner and i'm like who the hell did he
pull that off i mean he killed me like
three tenths in one corner that was it
you know i was three times behind how
did that happen
and what did you put it down to in the
end you do you think he was just
building up to it or is just those
special special abilities with
experience in the moments when it counts
having that said it you know having the
confidence the experience and and trying
something a bit you know crazy with the
card i was anyway the slowest but uh
trying to go for it and find out
something that was not written in the
book
and actually learn from that you know uh
and tried in the future as well to pull
some some outstanding performance
sometimes where you just feel confident
in the lap and you say okay i'm gonna
i'm gonna try it i had my own
experiences like that because i had
schumacher and hamilton is my teammate
so so you could imagine that i had the
occasional moment like that as well
along the way where it's just like it's
the same car and it's like how the hell
can they even physically humanly do
something like that in that moment it's
sometimes it's really big head
scratching
i'm sure they felt the same about you
some other time or about me
hopefully
hopefully um so then 2012 you you get
the call up to come back into formula
one which of course was a really cool
breakthrough for you to be in f1 two
years out then come back again that was
a big step with kimmy this time but it
started off to be a really tough tough
one for you i think the car was quite
good but you were crashing a lot is that
right that was the was that 2012 no
that's the perception from outside but
actually if you look at the races and so
on it's it's not
it's not right uh surprisingly i was my
third race i was on the podium you know
for a rookie that wasn't bad i was third
on the road on the grid in australia and
then pasteur
kind of pushed me off in the race
in malaysia i was raining it was my
mistake i spun
i wanted too much
and then
and then i was on the podium in canada i
finished second i was leading the the
european grandpa in valencia when the
alternator failed
uh
in monaco i was forced on a grid and and
michael tried to overtake me
through the left going on the starting
grid and that's never going to work
because the guard really come back to
the right and we touched
and there were a few touches and i don't
know why the reputation started there
and then there was staff from koshan
where i collided with with lewis
obviously in that race i could have done
much better but if we look at the
footages uh luis could have also
you know give me a little bit more room
or back up from the situation as he did
in 2000 when was it 2018 mexico is
sebastian vettel at the start
well you know uh he he backed off so
there were stickers put on my on my head
with with crashes but actually if we
look at all the incident and the races
and so on
there weren't that many
man you're a memory machine
like what what's up with that
can you remember every single race or
what i i've got an elephant memory for
some of the the stuff you know
especially but anyways even if you're
even if you're saying no it's not really
the truth but still the sticker was put
on your head that you're a mr mr
crushing all the time wasn't that tough
from you this external opinion that was
building up and the pressure from
outside wasn't that a tough moment in
your career yeah that was that was
probably one of the toughest you know uh
just because you've got that sticker put
you on on your on your head uh you've
already came to formula one once came
back tried to do the best you can
did it did a pretty good season you know
i was three four podiums in my first
year in formula one uh and then you've
got that sticker and then you need to
drive under your level just to avoid
anything else and then come back in 2013
and same thing initially i had to be
very careful and make sure that i would
clean that sticker from from my head and
that is that is tough work
wasn't that the moment also where you
started to work with a psychologist
yes correct that was about 2012 just so
i could you know i could understand um
what was happening and and as i say i've
made mistakes i'm not saying i didn't
make any mistakes but uh
um also i think the sticker was was
probably not not quite
accurate as such uh but yes i went i
went through that and and learned a lot
you know and uh i think what i wanted is
to win the race absolutely to the you
know from the first corner to to the
last one um because you know in formula
one that's you know if you're first at
the first corner life is is much easier
than if you are at the back
of course and and who um who convinced
you to take a psychologist it just came
from yourself or was it the team or
no it came it came from myself and uh i
met my psychologist once i met her
through an institute in in paris and we
only chatted like
five minutes
but i knew her and then i think that was
in june or something like that and then
in september after spa
i phoned her and i said okay well you
know i'm going to try to see what i can
fine-tune to make sure that i take the
right decision uh again in spa i was it
wasn't 100 million zero percent
the other but uh it was mainly me and i
say okay what can i do better to avoid
that that's
that situation
so we have that in common uh because i
was working with a psychologist in 2006
no 2007. so i worked very very intensely
throughout almost my entire career
every two days we did two hour sessions
um which was it was tougher than all the
physical training it was like absolutely
extreme
um so we have that in common but the
difference was that you actually spoke
about it which i think is very
courageous because in our world in f1
you're a bit of a loser if you uh if you
have a brain doctor helping you you know
a psychologist so that sucks a bit but
you were courageous enough always to
talk about which which i respect a lot
um
and what was your biggest uh what was
your biggest progress that you found in
in your work with a psychologist like
the biggest eye-opening moment or where
you can really see okay that that
definitely um had a positive change in
my life as a result of of that work
you know i think you
every time every year there are some
it's crazy we can always progress
another brain works you know
obviously i went through through some
tough moments in my career
not mentioning the 29th of november 2020
but also i became a father
a husband and that changed your life in
in many ways and you know sometimes you
just
you just need to add up to two different
situation uh for me 2013 i was doing a
an amazing season and without any curse
issue early in the year i think i could
have
become probably vice world champion
and and then 2014 my car was a piece of
rubber and
you know i was we were the slowest and
and you are ready to
win races you've done all your work and
then suddenly the tool you have in
between your hand is just not good and
uh that is tough and then you work on
that and
also i remember when i was leading the
race in 2013 in suzuka it was about the
first time i was properly leading the
race from lap one and i was thinking
don't crash don't crash because you know
all the tvs are watching you so don't
put it in the gravel
and uh after that i spoke to the
psychologist so this is you know this is
brand new i've never experienced
leading a formula one race as such so
we worked around that uh so you work
around the good moments but also around
the tough ones and what was one of those
toughest moments like you explained that
now like being scared that you're gonna
crash that obviously isn't very
beneficial to performing well uh those
kind of thoughts but is there any very
dark other dark moments where you say
like oh damn i was sitting at home and
and i i started to think that maybe i'm
just not good enough for for being a
formula one uh driver or is there any
like really really dark moments that you
had in that time
no i never really thought i wasn't good
enough to be in formula one but there
was some dark moment where you think
what why did i do that you know why
like to me two two in my career that i'm
really not proud of is japan 2012. uh
when i crashed to the start with uh with
mark webber and that was 100 my fault i
didn't even see him i was so focused on
trying to overtake the other car that i
didn't even see him
and then barcelona 2018 when i spun in
turn three and uh
and i wanted to just to swipe the car
back on track and and one from throttle
instead of jumping on a brake and you
know giving up the position but 2012
like with mark webber that was after a
string of other incidents already which
other people saw mostly as your as your
fault and and how do you then how did
you then work through that with your
psychologist this self-doubt that came
like why did i why am i making such
mistakes why why can't i do better than
that how do you how do you overcome that
well we you know we work through all the
steps and and
why is is this happening why you know uh
why didn't
in japan why he didn't i didn't even see
it i didn't i was so focused on i think
it was a sauber on my left who's kamui
kobayashi why was i so focused on not
losing the position and why didn't
didn't i accept to lose a position at
the time even if i could get him back
and and then obviously trying to survive
the criticism from other drivers you
know the journalists that's their job to
criticize your critics us you know they
they do all the time anyway uh so we're
used to it but when it comes from the
other drivers then it's a bit more
complicated and and it hurts more so
then i had to drive you know until korea
2013 every first lap i was driving under
my capacity under my capability just
because i wanted to avoid and i remember
before korea i had a chat with my
psychologist and she says no you can go
you can be you can be engaged in lap one
and say are you crazy i say you know
what i went through so yeah but i think
you're ready you know i think you can
you know you can do it and if you watch
on youtube that first lap in korea 2013
had a big fight with luis
and uh came out on top of it and we you
know and i was back to where i like to
be so that's cool so with the
psychologist you just risked ma
positioned yourself different on the
risk management and just
decided to
consciously take a little bit less risks
at all time to build back up to it was
that was really the the key out of it or
what yeah if we want to simplify it and
yes he was trying to to back up for some
time making sure that you know the
confidence would come back normally
and then eventually when
when we were ready just go for it
that sounds cool that sounds like really
smart uh a smart approach which not so
many other drivers i think would have
done in in that way so that's uh that
sounds great yeah i think it was you
know it was great and uh i'm still you
know i haven't stopped working with her
uh obviously
after the crash in bahrain there were
also some you know some different work
that we needed to do
uh just because you can't you can't be
so close from this without working on it
you know if i had been working i would
have had nightmares that would have i
don't even think if i could have jumped
back in a racing car
but um
but we worked through through through
that and through the process and through
everything
so
you know i think you always you always
become stronger and stronger and you
know you we i mean you and me we know
how to prepare physically for racing
cars you know we've done it for 20 years
but we still use a trainer right
so the brain is the same thing to me why
don't we use someone to train our brain
even though we know
you know and it's more complicated than
just doing biceps curls or pull-ups or
bench press to be fair
no it's not necessarily i think it's
it's a very similar approach to to get
the training right in the most efficient
way is also very complicated and and to
progress mentally it's similar and i can
only encourage everybody who's watching
or listening really take some time in
your life to educate yourself also about
the mental side learn there's so much
valuable information out there which is
so powerful for our lives i can really
recommend it it also had such a big
impact on on my life so we really um we
really share that um if it's okay i
would like to touch on the um on the on
the tough crash of course a bit later
just coming back again you were racing
kimmy of course in 2012 2013. quick
comparison kimmy alonso any ideas who
you'd say
you would put as the as the faster guy
ah
i think the faster would be would be
alonso over one lap
over a race distance kimi always would
find a solution to go fast whatever
would happen you would always go fast in
a race
and you sometimes didn't really know how
he was doing it or what no exactly uh
you know you would you would just he
would just drive and say yeah the car
was okay and you're like no the car was
not okay it was you know just doing
oversteering whatever
what was do you remember any really
funny moment with kimmy
well you know we were teammate for two
years and we we never really
spoke that much kimi was kimi um even
though
since he's got kids
for the further much better
but i remember in spa sitting spa i
think so we're in the truck and he came
to me comes to me and he says
congratulations on the son of your uh
the burst of your son
i was like i was shocked because you
know we never spoke and out of the blue
he knew i just had a baby so i was like
okay thank you kimmy but i didn't know
what to say
but since the birth of his children
though he's become a bit of a comedian
on instagram so i think he's uh he seems
to have changed then
yeah he's changed a lot and uh he's not
a great great guy i mean you know i
always love racing him on track because
you know
that he's always gonna
respect and give you the room and you
can have you know you you can go in
confidence fighting kimmy on track for
sure
uh and yeah since he's got kids it's
quite fun um let's go to some more some
more positive stuff like if you now look
back um the most
the best most beautiful moment in your
f1 career what would you what would you
put it what was it
you know it's difficult i didn't win a
race and i didn't win a championship so
it's easy when you win you know to to
pick uh not easy but you can pick that
one for me i had many podiums um
and then i had some some less good cars
but some good races you know that
question comes very often to me and i
can't really pick one moment up of my of
my career i've had i've had a lot of
good moments
my last podium you were there uh you
know in 2015 and that was obviously a
good moment we had the bailiffs in the
garage the team was the cow was was
taped to stay together
and here we are on the podium and uh
obviously some good races with haas as
well so um yeah plenty of good memories
but you you can definitely say that
you're going out of f1 now with a very
fulfilled uh fulfilled mindset of all
the things you've achieved right yeah
very much you know i obviously i i never
win a race i never uh i never i was
never world champion but uh
at the end
i've had the career that i you know even
better than i could have hoped at the
beginning um i've you know been there
ten years i've i've gone around the
questions
and i was watching winter testing and i
don't feel bad not being there you know
i think i've i've done my time uh i was
obviously if if you get a call from
mercedes or red bull of ferrari then you
know it's a competitive car so why you
want to jump back in but uh to be to be
back of the grid and not being able to
fight for wins and so on i think i've
done my time and you know i'm happy to
watch it i'm still a fan about it but
i've i'm okay with not being there
anymore
i'm not too sure about your uh mention
of ferrari there in that trilogy of
competitive cars but let's leave that
let's leave that aside
you have to put ferry as a competitive
car whatever you know even if they're
not just put it in there
i have that though that i always
watching f1 always somehow still
accompanies me with a little bit of
negativity that i'm thinking like oh
uh i i could be there it's strange
because i'm totally fulfilled as well
but it still has always a tiny negative
there when i'm watching but i think it's
always going to be always going to be
like that yeah i mean you know i i i i'm
lucky to race in something else and i
guess i'm i'm finding a lot of pleasure
in in racing something else so really
for me
f1 the chapter is kind of closed
if it's a if it's okay i would still
like to before we close it completely
just go of course into one of the one of
the most difficult uh moments for you
and i'd like to start with a comment of
yours
and your comment is 2017 or 2018 i never
liked it and i still don't like it
i think it was a very sad day for f1
when it came out
do you know what i'm talking about yes
the halo
yes this is a this is a comment of yours
about the halo
what uh what is your view now on that
well
jean-thought came to see me in bahrain
on my hospital bed
and he said you remember what you say
about the halo and they say jean there's
only the dumbass that don't change their
mind
i have changed my mind
okay that's reassuring
i'm very glad to hear that
um so if it's
if it's okay with you i of course we'd
like to touch a little bit on on your
crash as well i hope i hope that's okay
for you and the crash you i mean you
were 27 seconds in the blazing fire and
then it was 67 g of of impact um
do you remember i hope that it's okay
for you that just to to to revisit it a
little bit i can imagine it's not so
easy but um i think the the listeners
would also appreciate from
getting an insight into some of those
experiences um
do you remember if you were scared at
any point as it was happening or or
after when you were sitting in the in
the fire
no actually no i think the
the first thing is between the the touch
with kiviat and the impact there's only
like six tenths of a second so you don't
really get the time to realize you're
gonna
hit the quad rail at that speed and then
surprisingly the impact for me wasn't
that bad you know 67 g is a lot but i
didn't feel like it was it was bad so i
i ended my silbed i'm ready to jump out
of the car and then i'm stuck and then i
you know i thought well i'm gonna wait
and then
they're gonna come and help me you know
i didn't know if it was upside down it's
night races there's no light in the
cockpit so you don't see anything you
don't know where you are
and um and then i realized there's fire
so oh okay no i can't wait and then i
try to jump out and jump out and jump
out and i i realize i'm completely stuck
and
and i realize the situation is is not
good
and then at one point i thought that was
it that was my day you know it was that
was game over
and uh that's why i say i was to me i
was i don't know five ten seconds from
being death dead uh
and and eventually i thought about my
three kids and i said no
i can't i can't leave them without that
and that's all i find the energy the
last energy to
to manage to find a solution to jump out
of the car even though you know i i
could i could feel my hands with burning
you know normally when you you touch
something hot you would you touch it and
remove it but i would i would keep my
hands and straight into the fire because
that's the only
grip i had to jump out of the car
and my foot was stuck and i was pulling
so hard on my leg that even my ankle
could have stayed there i wouldn't care
you know i just wanted to be out of the
car
and um
eventually made it
and
that that moment where i was sliding and
i knew i was off that was you know kind
of the best moment of you know of my
life maybe just because i was going to
leave um
and uh then i was in shock obviously
then i was in shock from from what
happened and seeing the fire and so on
and seeing what i went through um but
also you know it teach me a lot about me
that um
i knew i never give up in my life and i
never gave up in in my hopes and dreams
and and
wish to win races and to compete but uh
this experience being in in such a
difficult situation uh and not giving up
on and you know putting all you have in
your head fighting as high as hard as
you can to to escape that fire um show
me how strong it can be in in tough
times
i get uh i get shivers uh
listening to that because i also
remember sitting in front of the tv um
watching and of course i can relate a
tiny bit because of knowing how it feels
to sit in that cockpit in that space
um
and but you didn't you didn't have any
fear even when you started even the
moment you realized your foot was stuck
you weren't you weren't scared no
no i was i was not scared um
you know at that time you can't you
don't have the time to be scared
uh and and as i said at one point i
almost accepted that
that was it you know i would
i would be dead um it's quite it's quite
a strange feeling and that's obviously
something i had to work on with my
psychologist because say how can you
kind of accept you know and people say
oh you see all your life and so on no i
didn't see any of that i see
i see peace
and
and like
the body that that kind of relax and and
it is it is a very strange feeling um i
don't i don't
wish anyone to try it because you know
it's it's not not something you want to
go
but
it makes you
100 times stronger a thousand times
stronger
and i i read that you even had time to
relate to nikki lauda in those tenths of
a second is that that's really true
yeah that's true it's it's
when i undo the seat belt i start jump
out i don't i cannot do it and then i
realize i'm on fire and then i thought
about niki lauda and i said no no you
know i don't know why it's the third one
of the first footage that came into my
mind was with nikki being stuck in his
car on fire and and leaving the same
situation
i wish i could i wish i could speak with
him about it you know
because he was such a character i mean
you've been working with nikki
and
you know he was he was yeah to me was he
was the best legend of formula one no he
was a very special person yeah
absolutely and he gave me so much as
well in my career you know so i'm i'm of
course very very grateful as well and
wait i just saw your helmet recently on
on the internet actually it was
incredibly burning how are how are your
hands doing now
well you know one is
the right
is good um
the left is a little bit less good
you know i i as i say i can almost live
normally
i can't i can't cope with cold uh i
cannot put sun for two years on it so i
need to put sun cream and gloves and so
on uh
it's painful 23 hours a day
uh i need to do rehab exercise every 10
minutes just to not lose mobility
so
it's not all pink it's not it's not nice
but i've got my two hands i can drive
car i can kill my kids i can
play with them and that's what matters
and um and how
how has this now has it changed you in
any way in in life having such a extreme
experience and knowing how vulnerable
life actually is do you catch yourself
now in life maybe spending that half
hour more with your kids when when you
would otherwise have done instagram or
is there any uh any change like that
yeah there's there's a beef on and after
29 11 20 you know for me that you can't
you can't go through an experience like
this and be the same
um so yes there's a there's a beef on an
after i know i enjoy life more more
small details as you say being with my
kids more
especially that this year with all the
travel sometimes i'm aware a little bit
longer and uh you know try just try to
we we take life for granted you know
exactly sometimes yeah
but it can go very quickly
and so you really you say there's really
a distinctive change in some moments of
your life now which as a result of that
yeah i even got myself my wife worried
at one point because i was after the
crash i was playing table tennis
and with my trainer in bahrain when i
was trying to come back for abu dhabi
and uh and we come back to to the room
and say who won i said i don't know we
didn't play for points she got worried
because i never played for not winning
and that happened
so now you just play for the enjoying
the moment in life yeah exactly
okay well that's powerful now that it's
really had such a such a lasting uh
lasting impact on than on on your life
in in that way yeah for sure it does
change everything and just the way also
the way i've seen on my racing and you
know i'm still doing it very
professionally and training and doing
things right but
also
i don't want to forget the fun of it
which which you know in professional
sport we tend to
um you say
you say in professional sport you tend
to forget the fun of it how to explain
that a little bit more detail than in
your f1 f1 career you say fun became
smaller and smaller and why yeah i think
so just because you know you've got the
pressure you need to perform um
and
you know at the end if you don't if you
don't win you don't have
that much fun that's what we do since
we're little you know and uh just
driving car is great but when you travel
21 grand prize around the world
get jet lag in every direction
and you go to the race and you know your
car is only capable of doing 16 or
something like that
even though driving
f1 car is absolutely outstanding
you get fun for one session or one run
in free practice one and then you come
back to the garage you see your three
second of the pace and then you know
it's gonna go
and the fun just kind of disappears
yeah no i can i can relate to that that
um but but of course i had the element
in the last couple of years of having a
fantastic car but even then the fun
becomes becomes smaller with time
because there's just so much else
happening so much so much expectation
and pressure and
and um and battles and politics and
everything which unfortunately um just
reduces that that fun element with time
now for sure it's you know you had the
best car but yeah you also had one of
the best teammates to beat and uh
at the end
there's almost no room for fun it's not
that we forget it is that there's almost
no room for it you know just because
every time you do something it has to be
for the performance uh
and to go for it and therefore
it
yeah the fun starts to go a little bit
away
yeah yeah um can i just i come back
again to the work you've done with your
psychologist now after the crash that
you had
last november um because i don't know if
maybe there's a few things that we can
pick out of course we haven't most of us
haven't had anywhere near as extreme
experiences but but maybe it's still
relatable for some some some big
failures we have in life or something
else can you pick out like one
particularly very interesting thing
piece of work that you did with a
psychologist to to work through that and
and to uh to not um have any negativity
from the crash to continue in your in
your life is there one particular point
well
i think you know every every experience
is is different and it's it's quite hard
to
relate uh something what i would say is
you know that life is life is beautiful
and worse living and and
you know most of the time there is a
solution and even though when i was in
the fire they could look like there was
no solution to to live
at the end there were one and i had to
dig deep
and and to fight for it but uh
at the end it worked so
i i'm not the type of guy that goes on
social media and gives you know uh live
uh lessons or stuff that we can see uh
sometimes um
and i think we all we're all different
in the way we we leave things and and
you know the way we learn things about
ourselves uh
but
you know i think one of the key in life
generally is to never give up
you know never give up on on your dream
on your wishes on what you're doing and
sometimes it just may
not look good or may look hard and not
be pretty but um
i mean
if you if you give up you never know
what the answer is going to be the the
positive really is that it changed my
life for the best just because i
realized that uh
clothes are worse from from not having
any more seconds so you know
it's almost like a second birthday uh
and every second is bonus so i guess
that's
but that's that's even more than the
psychologist myself i i realized that
and i need you know every morning i wake
up and i realize and i remind me myself
that i'm here and that is you know that
that is lucky to be here
um
so yeah life life is worth believing
that's really nice to hear but then at
the same time now you signed for
dalecoin racing in uh in uh indy cars so
are you then a little bit of a nut case
or what because uh you're coming from
this and you're going into a racing
that's even more dangerous because
you're racing on ovals where we know
unfortunately that the the risk is
higher um
i mean
you're comfortable now or after that was
it how was the feeling like before you
got back into the first time in the
racing car in del coin racing were you a
bit like i don't know if i'm gonna
be able to do this or
you know i was i was never worried for
testing um i
knew jumping back in the car because i
did it in bahrain i wanted to to sit in
the in the house
yeah thursday
yeah i think it was thursday um so five
days after the crash and i felt i didn't
feel any
anything strange anything unusual
i wasn't worried sitting in a car we you
know in in motorsport we accept the risk
this is
it's since we do go-karts you know i
broke my collarbone in go-karts and
and and we have had crashes and things
and we know it it's dangerous and and we
always try to make with the gpd and so
on we always try to make the the sport
safer from the bottom of the ladder
um
obviously there are things a little bit
different you mentioned overs i'm not
doing the the speed west so i'm not
doing texas no indy 500 which is one of
the biggest race in the world that
obviously i would like to have it on my
palmaris but uh
it's not so much for me it's more for my
my family and my kids and my wife not to
put them into the situation again
because you know when you drive at 400
kph and there's a crash it's a big one
most of the time we touch with the guys
they jump out okay
but for a moment you can you see the
crash and you don't know and i don't
want to put them through uh that that
face you know
the risk we accepted i mean
formula you cannot drive a car 330 kph
next to each other
fighting the limits driving through the
streets of monaco flat out
without knowing that there is the risk
is involved and you know we accept it we
measure it we're not crazy as you say we
uh
we
you know it is our life you know living
on the edge but knowing
which which side is the good side i
really respect also how you're showing
your vulnerability now in this moment
how you're saying hey i actually don't
know how it's going to be when i'll be
in the middle of the race start with
with 24 other cars going uh going flat
out in the racing car on a rolling race
start no which is
more crazy than the f1 race starts um so
i really appreciate that and at the same
time it's great to see the courage of
the courage that you're that you're
taking to just put you into that
situation and just go for it um
very very very strong
yeah i'm passionate about it i love
racing and you know even on my hospital
bed the first the first mission was
trying to be back in the car in abu
dhabi
and uh never really i thought about
quitting you know and a lot of people
would have understood if i said you know
i retired at the end of my career
it would have been almost normal
but we we are not normal you know we
we built to be champions we built to be
to be races to be competitors
and as long as you have that wish that
you want you are not done with what you
love doing then uh
you know it's hard to stop and as i say
formula one for me the chapter is it's
turned and
i'm happy with what i've done i don't
regret anything
but mother spot i am i don't feel like
i'm done with it and if i would stop now
i would feel always something a bit
you know not so positive
what is for you like the dream targets
one or two targets left in in
motorsports it would be winning uh
winning indycar championship of course
and yeah that would be nice uh le mans
24 hours endurance racing you know
sharing the cars with teammates uh
that's something that i
i did last year the mall 24s on esports
and
with my team and my teammates and we
crossed the finish line and we finished
fourth
and it was actually super special to
share that moment with with the guys
even though we weren't in the same room
but we were talking and chatting on
discord and it was a it was a special
moment and i thought that that day i
thought you know what i think i've had
enough of trying to be as fast as i can
on my own no i want to make sure that i
go fast with my team you know my
teammates my car goes fast and endurance
is definitely something that i want to
do yeah that's really nice i've heard so
much about that i'm from f1 drivers
going to indycar and saying it's uh to
to le mans saying it's such a refreshing
experience because in f1 it's so ego ego
focused and ego driven it's just you and
and on your own against the others
feeling wise even though you have a team
um and that's really refreshing to share
the the resp the responsibility with
other drivers like that as you were
saying sounds really uh sounds like a
really nice environment
yeah no for sure it's definitely
something i want to try and you know
indycar has got
it's got a very different mentality as
well from from formula one it's a single
seater but there's such a
i mean everything is open you
i went to the first test of the season
and the car was being set up on the
on the parking
but our car next to a rail racing team
next to penske
and there's no tents no bugs no hiding
and they're like no i mean they're all
the same cars best the best one does the
best job on track and that's it and you
share barbecue in the evening with the
drivers and then obviously in the
morning you put your race helmet and
then it's it's fighting and beating them
all but the atmosphere is is so
different that it's already
something that uh you know coming from
ten years in formula one it's a big
change
that's so nice to hear i think it sounds
like you're gonna have a really nice
time and and with the talent that you
have i mean you have the best chances to
win the championship also the next in
the next couple of years so
at this point thank you so much for uh
for taking the time for the chat and i
think everybody who's listening as well
wishes you so much success in your next
steps and uh and really respect for the
for for all the courage that you're uh
that you're bringing to this and to your
next steps um really impressive so thank
you very much and say hi to the family
please
i will same to you thank you for having
me say hi to the family
look after them and anyway we keep
talking and chatting here and there
thank you roman so bye-bye
oh and uh let me let where can everybody
follow you i can blend in your instagram
where can everybody follow your your
season uh
okay perfect so everybody follow roman
on instagram so you can watch the season
hopefully see you win again in indy cars
exactly